Guide to the Arthur Jack Viseltear papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, Speeches and other Statements, 1959 1989, undated; Series III
  - Unpublished
    - "333 Cedar Street" (Box 43)
      - Interviews (Box 45)
        - Transcriptions [notes, typescripts]
          - C. J. R. 3d year M.D. student, [1981] (Box 48, Folder 202)
          - Chaillet, J. Richard, 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 48, Folder 203-204)
          - Codish, Kay D.Office of Women in Medicine, 1981 (Box 48, Folder 205)
          - D. P. C. 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, [1981] (Box 48, Folder 206)
          - Duffy, Thomas, professor, Medicine, 1982 (Box 48, Folder 207)
          - Duncomb, David C. chaplain, 1981 (Box 48, Folder 208)
          - E. K. W. 2d year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 48, Folder 209)
          - E. S. M. 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 48, Folder 210)
          - F. E. M. assistant professor, Medicine, [198-] (Box 48, Folder 211)
          - F. E. R. H. 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 212)
          - F. E. T. assistant professor, Medicine, [198-] (Box 49, Folder 213)
          - Fryer, Regina Kenny, librarian, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 214)
          - G. A. N. 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 215)
          - G. C. R. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 216)
          - G. D. R. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 217)
          - Garber, J. E. 5th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 218-219)
          - Garcia-Blanco, Mariano, 4th year M.D./Ph. D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 220)
          - Goldman, Robert S. 4th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 221)
          - Guido, Annette D. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 222-223)
          - H. W. M. 4th year student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 224)
          - Homer, Robert J. 2d year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 225-226)
          - Horwitz, Ralph I. assistant professor, Medicine, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 227)
          - J. R. E. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 228)
          - J. S. E. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 229)
          - Kinder, Barbara, assistant professor, Surgery, 1982 (Box 49, Folder 230)
          - L. R. M.P.H./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 49, Folder 231)
          - L. R. associate professor, Surgery, 1982, 1983 (Box 49, Folder 232)
          - Levine, Robert J. professor, Internal Medicine, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 233)
          - M. A. C. librarian, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 234)
          - M. J. T. secretary, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 235)
          - M. S. K. librarian, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 236)
          - M. W. C. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 237)
          - M. W. M. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 238)
          - Matory, Yvedt L. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 239-240)
          - Nestler, Eric J. 4th year M.D./Ph.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 241)
          - O. F. N. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 242)
          - P. C. E. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 243)
          - P. H. A. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 244)
          - P. R. M. 4th year student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 245)
          - R. A. M. 2d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 246)
          - R. D. G. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 247)
          - R. M. T. librarian, [1981] (Box 50, Folder 248)
          - Roberts, Chris W. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 249)
          - S. B. C. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 250)
          - S. B. P. 2d year resident, Yale Medical School alumnus, [1981] (Box 50, Folder 251)
          - S. D. O. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 252)
          - Sartorelli, Alan C. chair, Pharmacology, 1982 (Box 50, Folder 253)
          - Spiro, Phillip M. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 50, Folder 254-255)
          - T. E. D. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 256)
          - T. L. A. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 257)
          - T. M. L. 3d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 258)
          - Thier, Samuel O. chairman, Internal Medicine, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 259)
          - V. E. W. 2d year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 260)
          - V. T. S. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 261)
          - Weil, Ulrich, clinical professor, Orthopedics, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 262)
          - Weinberg, David H. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 263)
          - Yeone, Frank E. 4th year M.D. student, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 264)
        - Research materials (Box 51)
          - Notes, [198-] (Box 51, Folder 265-269)
          - Board of Permanent Officers [copies, notes from minutes of 1915-1935], [198-] (Box 51, Folder 270)
          - Institute for Human Resources, [198-] (Box 51, Folder 271)
          - Service of memory and thanksgiving following the completion of the anatomy course, 1982
            - Audiocassette (tape 70) (Box 47)
            - Transcription, 1982 (Box 51, Folder 272)
    - "Adaptation of the Historical Method to Health Policy Determination: History and Health Policy", undated (Box 51, Folder 273)
    - "Applications of Statistical Analysis to Problems of Health in the Eighteenth Century", undated (Box 51, Folder 274)
    - "Medicare and History: An Essay Review", undated (Box 51, Folder 275)
    - "A Selected Anthology of Readings in the History of Hygiene and Public Health", undated (Box 51, Folder 276)
    - "Boating Enthusiasts", undated (Box 51, Folder 277)
  - Public Statements
    - Introductions (Box 51)
      - Rosen, George to HSA Colloquium, 1973 (Box 52, Folder 278)
      - Roemer, Milton as Sigerist Annual Lecturer, 1980 (Box 52, Folder 279)
      - First Annual George Rosen Lecture, 1986 (Box 52, Folder 280)
    - Lectures (Box 52)
      - Guest lectures [contributed to colleagues' courses or to seminars], 1963-1978 (Box 52, Folder 281)
      - "The Medical Care Case Study--Content and Intent", 1966 (Box 52, Folder 282)
      - "Case Study: Content and Intent", 1967 (Box 52, Folder 283)
      - "The California Medical-Economic Survey; Paul A. Dodd vs. the California Medical Association" [abstract], 1969 (Box 52, Folder 284)
      - "Financing Hospital Costs", 1969 (Box 52, Folder 285)
      - "Tobacco and Health", [197-] (Box 52, Folder 286)
      - "Health Insurance in California, 1910-1945", 1970 (Box 52, Folder 287)
      - "The Pneumonic Plague Epidemic of 1924 in Los Angeles", 1972 (Box 52, Folder 288)
      - "Health Insurance in California, 1915-1932" [notes], 1972 (Box 52, Folder 289)
      - "Government Policies and Legislation on Women and Health", 1973 (Box 52, Folder 290)
      - "National Disease Control and Consumer Health Education Act of 1973", 1975 (Box 52, Folder 291)
      - "Immunization and Public Policy: A Short History of the 1976 Swine Flu Legislation", 1977 (Box 52, Folder 292)
      - Plaque for Elizabeth Thomson, 1978 (Box 52, Folder 293)
      - "Charles-Edward Amory Winslow and the Heroic Age of American Public Health", 1981 (Box 52, Folder 294)
      - "The Formative Years of the Yale School of Medicine", 1981 (Box 52, Folder 295)
      - "Oath Ceremony, Yale School of Medicine", 1982, 1986, 1987 (Box 52, Folder 296)
      - "Orientation lecture", 1982, 1988 (Box 52, Folder 297)
      - "Antecedents to Contemporary Health Issues: History, Politics and the Policy of Health", 1983 (Box 52, Folder 298)
      - "Winternitz and Social Medicine", 1984 (Box 52, Folder 299)
      - "Oral History Aiding Recent History. 333 Cedar Street: A Chapter in Contemporary Medicine", 1986 (Box 52, Folder 300)
      - Remarks on receipt of the Francis Gilman Blake Award, 1988 (Box 52, Folder 301)
      - "The Ethos of Public Health", 1989 (Box 52, Folder 302)
      - "The Scope of Public Health Insights from C.E. A. Winslow", 1989 (Box 52, Folder 303)
      - Luncheon address to the class of 1993, 1989 (Box 52, Folder 304)
      - "The Eighteenth Century Lithontropics", undated (Box 52, Folder 305)
    - Radio talks
      - Introduction to Clement Markert's talk, "Cooperative Research, Patents, and Licensing," for "Science, Industry and the Medical School" radio series [tape 72], Undated (Box 47)
      - "Doctors in Society" in Council for Humanities "California Times, #15 [tape 71], Undated (Box 47)
- Teaching Files, 1965-1989; Series IV
  This series contains notes and outlines for courses Viseltear taught at three institutions. Files are arranged in alphabetical order by institution and then by the course abbreviation and number. All the Yale University courses are in one sequence regardless of the school or department in which they were given. In addition to courses shown as EPH [Epidemiology and Public Health], other public health courses are listed under MC [Medical Care] or HSA [Health Services Administration].
  Viseltear was faculty mentor for student public health projects in EPH110 course, "The Design and Implementation of Public Policy." The series includes interview outlines, meetings, and reports of the projects carried out in the local communities of Guilford, Madison, and Branford, Connecticut.
  The course outline for HM100, the history of medicine, which had stayed the same from 1977 1980, was entirely reworked in 1981. There are extensive subject notes associated with the reorganization.
  - California College of Medicine, 1966-1968 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - University of California, Los Angeles
    - Colloquium: Resistance to Medical Change in Historical Perspective, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Colloquium: Student Health Projects, 1967 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - PH 5: History of Epidemic Diseases, 1966 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - PH 100: Introduction to Principles of Public Health, Circa 1965-1969 (Box 53, Folder 5-13)
    - PH 109: History of Public Health, 196- (Box 53, Folder 14-16)
    - PH 109: History of Public Health, 1965-1968 (Box 54, Folder 17-18)
    - PH 200: Health Services Administration, Circa 1965-1969] (Box 54, Folder 19-20)
    - PH 202: Medical Care Administration, Circa 1965-1969] (Box 54, Folder 21)
    - PH 205: Historical Development of Modern Medicine, Circa 1965-1969] (Box 54, Folder 22)
    - PH 290: History of Public Health and Social Medicine [seminar], Circa 1965-1969] (Box 54, Folder 23-24)
  - Yale University
    - EPH 100: History of Public Health, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 25)
    - EPH 110: Introduction to Public Health, 1972-1979 (Box 54, Folder 26)
      - Projects
        - "Cedarville" [Guilford, CT], 1971-1972 (Box 54, Folder 27-28)
        - "Meadowville" [Madison, CT], 1973 (Box 54, Folder 29)
        - "Newtonville" [Branford, CT], 1972-1974 (Box 54, Folder 30-31)
    - EPH 114: Introduction to Public Health Policy, 1971-1973 (Box 55, Folder 32-33)
    - EPH 115: Introduction to Research Methods, 1971-1972 (Box 55, Folder 34)
    - EPH 500: Government and Health Policy, 1979 (Box 55, Folder 35)
    - EPH 510: Introduction to Public Health, 1987 (Box 55, Folder 36)
    - EPH 521: History of Public Health, 1980-1989 (Box 55, Folder 37-38)
    - EPH Colloquium, 1982 (Box 55, Folder 39)
    - Hist. 124: History of Technology, undated (Box 55, Folder 40)
    - Hist. 233/HSHM 321: Introduction to the History of Medicine, 1980-1981 (Box 55, Folder 41)
    - Hist. 403/Hist. 963: Topics in the History of American Medicine, 1983 (Box 55, Folder 42)
    - Hist. 419/Hist. 963b/HSM 329: The Physician in Modern Society, 1988 (Box 55, Folder 43)
    - Hist. 421: Topics in the History of American Medicine, 1985 (Box 55, Folder 44)
    - Hist. 424/HSHM 324: Topics in the History of Public Health, 1983-1984 (Box 55, Folder 45)
    - Hist. 425/HMLS 729: The Physician in Modern Society, 1989 (Box 55, Folder 46)
    - Hist. 429/HSHM 324: Topics in the History of Medicine and Public Health, 1985 (Box 55, Folder 47)
    - HM 100: History of Medicine
      - Notes (Box 55)
        - General, [197-], undated (Box 55, Folder 48-51)
        - General, undated (Box 56, Folder 52)
        - American medicine, [198-], undated (Box 56, Folder 53-54)
        - Arabic, medieval medicine, undated (Box 56, Folder 55)
        - Archaic medicine, undated (Box 56, Folder 56)
        - Bacteriology, undated (Box 56, Folder 57)
        - Clinician, 1988 (Box 56, Folder 58)
        - Concluding lecture, 198- (Box 56, Folder 59-60)
        - Epidemic disease, undated (Box 56, Folder 61)
        - Epidemiologists, undated (Box 56, Folder 62)
        - Galen, undated (Box 56, Folder 63)
        - Government and health policy, 1985-1989 (Box 56, Folder 64-66)
        - Greek medicine, undated (Box 56, Folder 67)
        - Health insurance, 198- (Box 56, Folder 68)
        - History of anatomy, undated (Box 56, Folder 69)
        - National Institutes of Health, 198- (Box 57, Folder 70)
        - Nineteenth century public health, undated (Box 57, Folder 71)
        - Non-physicians, 198- (Box 57, Folder 72)
        - Plague, undated (Box 57, Folder 73)
        - Reformer, 198- (Box 57, Folder 74)
        - Roman and medieval medicine, undated (Box 57, Folder 75)
        - Rosen, George [compiled by], undated (Box 57, Folder 76-77)
        - Scientist, 198- (Box 57, Folder 78)
        - Sixteenth to eighteenth century medicine, undated (Box 57, Folder 79)
        - Smallpox, undated (Box 57, Folder 80)
        - Student, 1985-1989 (Box 57, Folder 81-82)
        - Teacher, 198- (Box 57, Folder 83)
        - Virchow, Rudolph, undated (Box 57, Folder 84)
      - Outlines, 1978-1985 (Box 57, Folder 85-86)
      - Outlines, 1987-1988 (Box 58, Folder 87)
    - HM 281: Development of Modern Medicine [notes from George Rosen], undated (Box 58, Folder 88)
    - HSA 114: Government and Health Policy, 1971-1981 (Box 58, Folder 89-96)
    - HSA 115: Executive Branch and Health Care in America, 1974-1977 (Box 58, Folder 97-98)
    - HSA 147/HSM 136: Health and Disease in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries, 1975 (Box 59, Folder 99)
    - HSA 170: Introduction to Health Services, 1969-1972 (Box 59, Folder 100)
    - HSA 177: Special Studies in Health Administration, 1972 (Box 59, Folder 101)
    - HSA 321: Introduction to the History of Medicine [exams], 1980 (Box 59, Folder 102)
    - HSA 514: Government and Health Policy, 1974-1987 (Box 59, Folder 103-112)
    - HSA 515: Executive Branch and Public Policy, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 113)
    - HSA 570: Student Projects on the implementation of the Connecticut Emergency Medical Services Law of 1977 (Box 60, Folder 114)
    - HSA 678: History and Health Policy, 1986-1987 (Box 60, Folder 115)
    - HYSM 321/721: Introduction to the History of Medicine, 1977-1978 (Box 60, Folder 116-117)
    - MC 278: History and Public Health Policy, 1969-1973 (Box 60, Folder 118-122)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Seminar: The Physician in Modern Society: Antecedents to Contemporary Health Issues, 1978-1980 (Box 60, Folder 123)
    - PH 290: History of Public Health and Social Medicine, undated (Box 60, Folder 124-126)
    - Sy 88: History, Politics and the Policy of Health, 1977 (Box 60, Folder 127)
    - Miscellaneous course related materials, undated (Box 60, Folder 128)
    - "Health Manpower" [student workshop] (Box 47)
      [See: tapes 73, 74, 75]
- Subject Files, 1969-1986, undated; Series V
  This series contains files on topics about which Viseltear wrote and lectured but which could not be positively associated with a particular course or publication. The notes have been filed by subject, in alphabetical order. Much of the material is undated. The notes are predominantly handwritten, though the files also include a few photocopies. The large numbers of government and organizational pamphlets and newspaper clippings that Viseltear accumulated have not been retained.
  - Abortion, 1969-1970 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Cancer, [197-] (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Environmental quality, [197-] (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Health Manpower, [197-]-[198-] (Box 61, Folder 4 - 6)
  - Historical methodology, undated (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - History, undated (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - History of mental illness, undated (Box 61, Folder 9)
  - History of public health in United States, undated (Box 61, Folder 10)
  - Hygiene in antiquity, undated (Box 61, Folder 11)
  - Leprosy, undated (Box 61, Folder 12)
  - Medical and public health individuals, undated (Box 61, Folder 13)
  - Medical education, [198-] (Box 61, Folder 14)
  - Medical ethics, [197-] (Box 61, Folder 15)
  - Mental health, 1979, undated (Box 61, Folder 16)
  - Pasteur, Koch, Lister, undated (Box 61, Folder 17)
  - Pharmaceutical industry, [198-] (Box 61, Folder 18)
  - Physicians in nineteenth century England, undated (Box 61, Folder 19)
  - Poverty, [197-] (Box 61, Folder 20)
  - Preventive medicine, 1970-[198-] (Box 62, Folder 21)
  - Public health issues, undated (Box 62, Folder 22)
  - SST [Supersonic Transport], [1970] (Box 62, Folder 23)
  - Science, history and academe, 1981-1986 (Box 62, Folder 24)
  - Social medicine, undated (Box 62, Folder 25)
  - State medicine, undated (Box 62, Folder 26)
  - Syphilis, undated (Box 62, Folder 27)
  - Technology, undated (Box 62, Folder 28)
- Personal Papers and Photographs, 1953-1990, undated; Series VI
  This series includes biographical information, memorabilia, reminiscences, and diaries, as well as a few personal photographs. "Reminiscences...1938 1969" was written in 1986 1987 as a preamble to the diaries which Viseltear started keeping in 1974. The reminiscences recall Viseltear's home, parents, neighborhood, and emphasize his years at DeWitt Clinton High School, Tulane University, and then at UCLA. He describes his transition from a pre medical student to a student of history and public health
  There are eighteen volumes of diaries from 1974 March to 1989 November. Viseltear usually wrote in them several times a week and added occasional supplemental entries to amplify them further. Diary pages are occasionally interleaved with invitations, letters, clippings, and memorabilia. Viseltear reports discussions with colleagues, his views on events and their political and strategic implications, as well as musings on personal happenings. He evaluates himself, his work, his colleagues, and his friends. The diaries begin with his experience as a Robert Wood Johnson Health Policy Fellow and provide details and impressions of his daily responsibilities as the member of a congressman's staff. They describe his return to academic life and also record personal events, continuing until a month before his death. There are also two notebooks of separate diary entries in the folder labeled "Personal notes."
  - Personal papers
    - Address book, [196-] (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Appointment books, 1963-1988 (Box 63, Folder 2 - 8)
    - Biographical information
      - General, 1960-1989 (Box 63, Folder 9)
      - Appointments, 1970-1979 (Box 63, Folder 10)
      - McMaster University, 1975 (Box 63, Folder 11)
      - Memorial service and remembrances, 1990 (Box 63, Folder 12)
      - Kámpe de Fériet, J., 1967-1989 (Box 63, Folder 13)
      - Tenure review, 1978 (Box 63, Folder 14)
    - Clippings, 1972-1986, undated (Box 63, Folder 15)
    - Diaries
      - Reminiscences, [1938-1969] 1986-1987 (Box 64, Folder 16)
      - Book 1-Book 8, 1974 March 11-1980 August 10 (Box 64, Folder 17 - 20)
      - Book 9-Book 15, 1980 August 11-1987 February 8 (Box 65, Folder 21 - 25)
      - Book 16-Book 18, 1987 February - 1989 November 17 (Box 66, Folder 26 - 28)
    - Memorabilia
      - General, 1953-1990, undated (Box 67, Folder 29 - 30)
      - DeWitt Clinton High School, 1965-1988 (Box 67, Folder 31)
    - Personal notes, [ca. 1963-1988] (Box 67, Folder 32)
    - Student notes
      - Epidemiology, 1960-1963 (Box 67, Folder 33 - 34)
      - Europe in the seventeenth century, 1960 (Box 67, Folder 35)
      - History, undated (Box 67, Folder 36)
      - Nineteenth century thought, 1961 (Box 67, Folder 37)
  - Photographs, 1960-1988, undated (Box 68, Folder 38 - 40)